Roman Hubbell family papers, 1899-1982
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Roman Hubbell family papers, 1899-1982
MS 322
Roman Hubbell Family
The papers in this collection are arranged in five series: Family History and Reminiscences, Correspondence, Business and Financial Records, Photographs, and Printed Materials. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence to and from Roman and Dorothy Hubbell relating to their family, friends and business ventures. Primary correspondents include anthropologist, Gladys Reichard, and Commissioner of Indian Affairs, John Collier.
6 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Roman Hubbell (1891-1957) was the second son of John Lorenzo Hubbell (1853-1930), noted pioneer Indian trader and founder of the J. L. Hubbell Trading Post at Ganado in Arizona Territory, 1876. The area surrounding the trading post eventually became part of the Navajo Reservation. Over the years Don Lorenzo, as he came to be called, opened additional trading post locations in New Mexico and Arizona and gained fame as a trader in Navajo rugs.
Don Lorenzo's two sons, Lorenzo, Jr. (1883-1942) and Roman succeeded their father in carrying on his trading post operations; and Roman developed a reputation as an advocate for the Indians in their relations with the federal government. After the death of Roman's first wife, he married Dorothy Smith (1899-1993) who assisted in the management of the family's business interests. Dorothy continued to run the trading post as a museum after Roman's death in 1957, until it was purchased by the National Park Service as a designated National Historic Site in 1965.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series.
Series I: Family History and Reminiscences, 1930-1971
Series II: Correspondence, 1899-1979
Series III: Business and Financial Records, 1919-1982
Series IV: Photographs, ca. 1900-1965
Series V: Printed Materials, 1928-1970s
Scope and Content Note
The papers in this collection are arranged in five series: Family History and Reminiscences, Correspondence, Business and Financial Records, Photographs, and Printed Materials. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence to and from Roman and Dorothy Hubbell relating to their family, friends and business ventures. Primary correspondents include anthropologist, Gladys Reichard, and Commissioner of Indian Affairs, John Collier.
The Personal Correspondence Series contains the transcript of an interview with Dorothy Hubbell by Frank McNitt which relates to Mrs. Hubbell's recollections of Don Lorenzo Hubbell during her early years at the Post. There is also a series of interviews with Mrs. Hubbell in the Hubbell Trading Post as National Historic Site Series which reconstructs the history of the trading post and its collection of art, furnishings, and Indian crafts. Photographs in the collection include members of the Hubbell family, portraits of individuals visiting the Post such as Theodore Roosevelt, Howard Pyle, Gladys Reichard, and John Collier. There are also photographs of Ganado and other trading posts, other Hubbell business operations, and Navajo weavers and participants in traveling exhibitions to Texas and New York.
Access Terms
Hubbell, Roman, 1891-1957
Hubbell, Dorothy Smith
Hubbell family -- Archives
Merchants -- Arizona -- History -- Sources
Trading posts
Trading posts -- Arizona -- Ganado Region
Ganado (Ariz.) -- History -- Sources
Hubbell Trading Post National Historic Site (Ganado, Ariz.) -- Archives
Navajo Indian Reservation -- History -- Sources
Southwest, New -- History -- 1848 -- Sources
Correspondence
Photographs
Related Materials
Hubbell Trading Post Records (AZ 375) are also located at the University of Arizona Library Special Collections.
Container List
- Series I: Family History and Reminiscences, 1930-1971
  Contains family record of births and deaths, a genealogical chart for the Hubbell family, reminiscences by John Lorenzo Hubbell, titled "Fifty Years an Indian Trader" (15 pages) and by Madge W. Hubbell, titled "As It Was Then" (56 pages).
  - Family History and Reminiscences. 1930-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1899-1979
  - Family, 1933-1962
    Family correspondence includes letters to and from Dorothy Hubbell, Lorenzo Hubbell, John L. Hubbell, Roman Hubbell, and LaCharles Eckel concerning activities at Ganado, education of the Hubbell children, and condolences on the deaths of Lorenzo Hubbell, Jr. and Roman Hubbell.
    - Eckel, LaCharles. 1933-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hubbell family. 1937-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hubbell, Lorenzo, Jr., condolences. 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Hubbell, John L. 1934-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Hubbell, Roman, Jr. 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Hubbell, Roman, condolences. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personal, 1899-1975
    Consists primarily of incoming letters and carbons of some outgoing, from personal and professional friends of Roman and Dorothy Hubbell. Many of the correspondents visited the Hubbell Trading Post to enjoy the scenic beauty of the area and to purchase rugs, ceramic vessels, and other trading post items. Of note are letters from Laura Armer concerning the exhibition of a movie, "The Mountain Chant;" from Witter Bynner about the United China Relief Fund donation drives during World War II; from Carl Hayden on military and education appointments for Hubbell children (additional Hayden letters in Hubbell Post National Historic Site folder); from Ruth Knight about the airing of a CBS radio series "Death Valley Days" segment titled "White Medicine Man" based on Roman Hubbell's assistance to the Navajos during a snow storm; with Frank McNitt concerning his research on the Hubbells including an interview with Dorothy Hubbell regarding Don Lorenzo Hubbell and life at Ganado; with anthropologist, Gladys Reichard on mutual friends, travels, and her projects; and artist, Frederic Allen Williams on his travels and exhibitions of sculptures.
    - A. 1935-1969 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - American Red Cross. 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Armer, Laura Adams & Sidney. 1928-1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - B. 1934-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Bynner, Witter. 1930-1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - C-H. 1899-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6-11)
    - Hayden, Carl. 1938-1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - I-K. 1938-1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Knight, Ruth Adams. 1941-1946 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - L-M. 1927-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - McNitt, Frank. 1958-1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - N-Q. 1931-1974 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - R-T. 1931-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Reichard, Gladys. 1934-1955 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Republican Party. 1935-1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - U-Z. 1934-1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Wiliams, Ferderic Allen. 1942-1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous. 1928-1949 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Roman Hubbell Navajo Tours, 1931-1965
    Contains letters from travel agencies, journalists, hotels, guest ranches, and tourists regarding coming to the area, the Hubbell Trading Post, lodging, sightseeing, or purchasing goods from the Post. Roman Hubbell operated this tour service in the late 1930s and early 1940s. Of note are letters from movie director, Fritz Lang of Universal Studios, and artist, William R. Leigh.
    - A. 1938-1960 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Atchison, Topeka & Santa Fe. 1931-1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - B-C. 1936-1956 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
    - Coapman, Wall G. 1940-1947 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - D-J. 1938-1963 (Box 4, Folder 7-12)
    - K-L. 1934-1952 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - Lang, Fritz. 1938-1940 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Leigh, William R. and Traphagen, Ethel. 1938-1958 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Luckie, Dorothy P. 1939-1949 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - M. 1937-1946 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - McFie, Amelia. 1938 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Motor News. 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - N-P. 1938-1950 (Box 5, Folder 10-12)
    - Page, Katherine. 1934-1950 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Q-S. 1934-1957 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - Santa Fe Trailways. 1939-1942 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - T-U. 1938-1949 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - Universal Studios. 1944 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - V-W. 1938-1965 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
    - Ward Hicks Advertising. 1938-1946 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Werntz, Carl. 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - X-Z. 1933-1950 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified and Miscellaneous. 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - J.L. Hubbell Trading Post, 1923-1969
    Miscellaneous letters sent from the Post on a wide variety of issues including merchandise inquiries, impounded goods, accounts owed, and letters from employees. Of special note are letters from artist, E. A. Burbank, and four folders of correspondence relating to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, John Collier, and the American Indian Defense Association; issues such as state congressional delegations; relief funds for Navajo stock; Navajo religion and ceremonies; land use; traders; schools; events leading up to Collier's appointment as Commissioner; Collier's resignation; and the appointment of succeeding commissioner, John R. Nichols.
    - A-H. 1935-1965 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Burbank, E.A. 1935-1947 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Employee Letters. 1935-1967 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - I-Z. 1923-1969 (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
    - U.S. Commissioner Indian Affairs, John Collier. 1924-1950 (Box 7, Folder 8-11)
    - Miscellaneous. No Date (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Hubbell Trading Post as National Historic Site, 1957-1979
    The first two folders contain correspondence including letters from visitors to the Post expressing their views on its historical importance and support for the establishment of a National Historic Site. The next three folders document the struggle in the early 1960s to obtain National Historic Site status for the Post which was achieved in 1965. Selected correspondents include Clinton P. Anderson, Paul Fanin, Carl Hayden, Morris K. Udall, the National Park Service, and personnel at Hubbell Trading Post National Historic Site. Additional information and clippings on this topic are located in the Printed Materials series of this collection. The last three folders contain inventories which serve to document the physical condition and artifacts of the Post at the time it was acquired by the National Park Service and an interview with Dorothy Hubbell by a National Park Service curator.
    - Tourist letters/history. 1957-1964 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Interest in National Historic Site Bill. 1957-1976 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence. 1959-1979 (Box 8, Folder 3-5)
    - Furnishing plans for Hubbell home. 1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Inventories of Hubbell Trading Post. 1975-1982 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Interview: Dorothy Hubbell by David M. Brugge. 1969 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Series III: Business and Financial Records, 1919-1982
  Contains financial and legal records relating to land and buildings purchased by the Hubbell family, stocks, leases, personal tax returns, and estate and bankruptcy proceedings.
  - Personal, 1919-1982
    - Contracts and deeds. 1919-1968 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Lease, Standard Oil Company, 1961-1982 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Stocks. 1931-1934 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Taxes. 1944-1965 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - General. 1919-1974 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Roman Hubbell Navajo Tours, 1934-1946
    Contains correspondence, legal and financial records relative to the operation of a tour company, including state and federal regulations, and tariff and rate charges filed with these agencies.
    - Apache County Assessor. 1938-1941 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Arizona Corporation Commission. 1938-1943 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Arizona Highway Department. 1938-1941 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Banking Records. 1936-1945 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Equipment leases. 1939-1942 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Insurance. 1938-1943 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission. 1937-1943 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - New Mexico Corporation Commission. 1934-1946 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - New Mexico Motor Vehicle Division. 1934-1942 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Transportation Rules & Regulations. 1937-1942 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous. ca. 1938-1942 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - J.L. Hubbell Trading Post, 1931-1975
    Contains correspondence, receipts, invoices, and tax returns for Hubbell Trading Post. Also includes three files on other family business ventures, the largest of which documents the activities of the Hubbell Truck Line under three subfiles, Gallup-Farmington Freight Line, 1931-1939; Mail Service, 1933-1937; and Fort Wingate Project, 1941.
    - Accountants. 1946-1975 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Insurance. 1956-1969 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - General. 1941-1967 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Tax returns. 1951-1966 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
    - Casa Don Lorenzo. 1950 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Hubbell Truck Lines. 1931-1941 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Lorenzo Hubbell Motor Company. 1946-1952 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Photographs, ca. 1900-1965
  Contains mostly black and white, with some color photographs, and a few negatives of people and places on the reservation. The bulk of the photographs document the Hubbell family, especially Roman Hubbell's activities with Navajo Indians in the promotion of Arizona as a tourist attraction; the Hubbell Post at Ganado; and Roman Hubbell Navajo Tours. In the family photographs are portraits of three generations of Hubbells. Of interest are a photograph of J. L. Hubbell with Theodore Roosevelt at Walpi in 1914, and Roman Hubbell with John Collier at Window Rock, c. 1940s. There are photographs of Ganado and Little Bridge Trading Post. Politicians campaigning or officiating at ceremonies in the area include Barry Goldwater, Stewart Udall, Robert Taft and Howard Pyle. Navajo medicine men, leaders, weavers, and families are also represented.
  - Texas Frontier Centennial. 1936 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Hubbell family. ca. 1900-1936 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Portraits. ca. 1928-1962 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Marble Canyon. 1938 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Navajo National Monument dedication. ca. 1965 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Places, unidentified. ca. 1940-1960 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Portraits, unidentified. ca. 1910s-1950s (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Little Bridge Trading Post. ca. 1950 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Ganado. 1930s-1960s (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Arizona Unlimited Exhibition. 1948 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Colorado River Boat Trip. 1950s (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Portraits, Navajos. ca. 1920s-1950s (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Navajo weavers and rugs. ca. 1920s-1960s (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Roman Hubbell Navajo Tours. 1938-1940s (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Navajo weavers and rug. No Date (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Series V: Printed Materials, 1928-1970s
  Contains advertisements for various businesses and miscellaneous matters on topics relating to Navajos, Ganado, and Arizona. Of note in the general file is a copy of Father Berard Haile's essay, "Some Cultural Aspects of the Navajo Mission," c. 1934; and "Pageant of Navajo History," presented by Navajo schools at the Navajo Tribal Fair in 1940. The bulk of this series consists of newspaper clippings on Ganado and feature stories on the Hubbell Post and family.
  - Advertisements. 1940s-1960s (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Advertisements and news clippings. 1930s-1940s (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Clippings on Establishment of Hubbell National Historic Site. 1960s-1970s (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Clippings. 1930s-1970s (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - General. 1928-1950s (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - General: Navajo, Hubbell, Arizona. 1930s-1940s (Box 11, Folder 21)